翻译: 榕树下的守望者
yipeng.lofter.com
这里是博克岛 狂风呼啸 没有阳光的气候
This is Berk, boasting the kind of balmy, fun-in-the-sun climate
恶劣到可以冻坏你的脾脏
that will give you frostbite on your spleen.
我们一年一度的节日
The one upside is our annual holiday.
我们称之为Snoggletog
We call it Snoggletog.
为什么我们会选择这样一个愚蠢的名字仍是一个谜
Why we chose such a stupid name remains a mystery.
但随着漫长的战争的结束
But with the war long over...
以及龙和我们一起生活 今年的Snoggletog节
...and dragons living amongst us, this year's Snoggletog...
一定会成为一段难以磨灭的记忆
...promises to be one to remember.
好了 好了 我来了
OK, OK! I'm coming!
早上好 "专横先生"
Good morning, Mr. Bossy.
你一定要总是那么早就叫醒我去飞行吗
Do you always have to wake me up so early to go flying...?
破假肢
Stupid leg.
谢谢啦 伙计 我没事
Thanks, buddy. I'm OK.
嗯 我们现在可以去飞行啦
Yeah, we can go flying now.
呦 呦 什么? 呦
Eww! Eww! What?! Eww!
无牙
Toothless!
来吧 让我们瞧瞧你今天能做到什么程度
Come on! Let's see what you got today!
耶 你准备好了吗
Yeah! OK, you ready?
放轻松
Easy...
太棒了 终于成功了
Yes! Finally!
对 对 不 不 那个应该挂高点
Yes, yes... No, no! That one a wee bit higher!
-这里? -那里 就是那里
- Here? - There! That's the spot!
呀
Roar!
干得好 Meatlug
Attaboy, Meatlug.
准备好了吗 姑娘
Are you ready, girl?
诸神啊
By Odin's beard, Gobber,
维京人居然和龙一起过节
Vikings spending the winter holiday with dragons!
-祖先们会怎么说呢 -他们肯定会认为我们疯了
- What would the fathers say? - They'd think we'd lost our minds.
干得好 干得好 你们都干得很好
Well done! Well done. All of you!
我从未想过我会活着看到今天 博克岛一派和平景象
I never thought I'd live to see this day: peace on the island of Berk.
这肯定是我们未曾见过的最盛大的节日
This will surely be the greatest holiday we've ever seen.
搞什么鬼
What the...?
雷神搞什么鬼
What in Thor's name?
回来 你们干什么去
Come back! What are you doing?
Meatlug
Meatlug!
-怎么了? -发生什么事了?
- What's going on? - What's happening?
希卡普在哪?
Where's Hiccup?
你觉得怎样 伙计? 想再来一次吗?
What do you say, bud? Wanna go again?
哇
Whoa!
哇 哇 哇
Whoa! Whoa! Whoa!
哦 不 我的头盔
Oh, no, my helmet!
哇
Whoa!
无牙 不 不 不 不 不 不 不
Toothless! No, no, no, no! No, no, no!
哇 哇 等等 无牙 停下
Whoa, whoa, wait! Toothless! Stop!
我待会再把它拿回来 伙计
We'll get it later, buddy.
我们要回去弄明白究竟发生了什么
We need to get back and find out what's going on.
怎么了 你要去哪里?
What's the matter? Where are you going?
不 不 不 别走 Stormfly 别走 求你了
No, no, no, don't leave, Stormfly! Don't go! Please?
-Astrid -Hiccup 怎么回事?
- Astrid! - Hiccup! What's going on?
它们要去哪?
Where are they going?
-它们为什么要离开? -发生什么事了?
- Why did they leave? - What's happening?!
如果它们再也不回来了怎么办?
What if they never come back?!
-请停下来 -冷静
- Stop, please! - Calm down!
给他说话的机会
Give him a chance to speak!
Hiccup 我们所有人的龙要去哪?
Hiccup, where are all of our dragons going?
爸 我不知道
Dad, I don't know.
它们要去哪? Snoggletog节办不成了
Where'd they go? Snoggletog is ruined!
办得成 我们是维京人
It's not ruined! We're Vikings!
我们世世代代在没有龙的情况下都完美地完成了节日庆祝活动
We've been perfectly happy celebrating without dragons for generations.
没有道理我们不能再来一遍
And there's no reason we can't do it again.
现在 我们不知道它们去了哪
Now, we don't know where they've gone off to.
但我们要对它们能尽快回来充满信心
But we have to have faith that they'll be back again soon.
-我说得对吗? -你说得对 我们是维京人
- Am I right? - You're right! We are Vikings!
我们坚韧不拔…大多时候是啦
We're tough... most of the time.
让我们唱些Snoggletog歌
Let's sing some Snoggletog songs.
-真让人诅丧 -我知道
- That was depressing. - I know.
人家还期盼着跟Stormfly过节呢
I was looking forward to spending the holiday with Stormfly.
你怎么那么高兴啊? 你不想念Meatlug吗
What are you so happy about? Don't you miss Meatlug?
我?
Me?
哦 对喔
Oh, yeah.
我好想念它啊
I miss him so much!
嗯 晚安
Well, good night.
我想到了一个主意 让我们创造一些节日传统
I've got an idea. Let's come up with a bunch of new holiday traditions.
你们知道的 为了忘记悲伤
You know, to bury the sadness.
其实 Astrid说得有道理
Actually, Astrid might be onto something.
说得轻巧 你的龙没有你哪也去不了
Easy for you to say. Your dragon can't go anywhere without you.
肯定很棒吧
Must be nice.
牦牛奶 喝些牦牛奶
Yak nog! Get your yak nog!
来吧 来份泡泡多的 欢欣美味杯
Come on! Get a frothy, delicious cup of cheer!
嘿 大家伙 都来尝尝我为节日特制的新饮料
Hey, you guys, try this tasty new beverage I made for the holiday.
-这是什么味道? 是从你身上的发出来的吗 -是牦牛奶的味道
- What's the smell? Is that you? - It's yak nog!
如果我喝下它 我就会吐得哪里都是
If I drink that, I'm gonna yak nog all over the place.
或许你宁愿我在你脸上打上几拳?
Maybe you'd rather taste a punch in the face?
Astrid 听起来不错 我来一杯
Astrid, it sounds delightful. I'd love a mug.
你们真得尝尝这牦牛奶
You can really taste the yak.
-赞 这是什么? -你要尝尝吗?
- Yum! What is that? - You wanna try some?
这是我新制的传统饮料
It's my new traditional drink.
哦 你知道 嗯
Oh, you know, um,
我突然加说不清为什么地改变了我的想法
I have suddenly and inexplicably changed my mind.
那好吧 你都不知道你错过了什么
Well, you don't know what you're missing.
我确信Hiccup一定会喜欢这饮料
I bet Hiccup will love this.
你是在哭吗
Are you crying?
-Hiccup? -嗯 我在这 Astrid 就来
- Hiccup? - Yeah, I'm over here, Astrid. Coming.
给你 节日快乐 来自我的真挚祝福哟
Here. Happy holidays. From me to you.
-谢谢 夫人 -你在忙什么呢?
- Thank you, milady. - What are you up to?
好吧 你会认为我疯了
OK, you're gonna think I'm crazy,
但我就是不能停止考虑Tuffnut昨晚说的话
but I just couldn't stop thinking about what Tuffnut said last night.
无牙不能像其它的龙那样自由来去
Toothless can't come and go like the other dragons,
那是不公平的 我一夜未眠
and that's just not fair. I was up all night,
我想我找到了修复的办法
and I think I found a way to fix that.
不是吧 你为它做了新尾巴?
No way! You built him a new tail?
那它就可以在没有你的情况下自由飞翔
So he's gonna be able to fly without you!
嗯嗯
Mm-hmm.
哇 多棒的礼物啊
Wow! What a great gift.
万一它一去不返呢?
What if he never comes back?
-我在说啥呢? 它当然会回来 -嗯
- What am I saying? Of course he will. - Mm-hmm.
嗯 我要去传播更多的的节日欢乐 你真棒
Well, I'm gonna go spread some more holiday cheer. You're amazing!
无牙 下来 伙计 我有东西给你
Toothless! Come on down, bud! I got something for you.
你觉得如何? 嗯
What do you think of that? Yeah.
你能不能安定下来啊
Would you just settle down!
无牙 拜托 伙计 让我把这给你装上
Toothless, come on, bud. Let me get this on you.
对 你会喜欢这玩意的
Yeah. You are going to love this.
好了
OK.
不 不 不 无牙 停下 求你了 等等 无牙 求你了
No, no, no! Toothless, stop! Please, wait! Toothless, please!
好了 看到没? 明白了吧?
There you go. See? Got it?
无牙 哇
Toothless... Whoa!
无牙
Toothless!
我就知道你会回来
I knew you'd come back!
哇
Whoa!
早上好 儿子
Morning, son.
嘿 爸爸
Hey, Dad.
很高兴看到你起床了 我在找你的头盔
Glad you're up. I was looking for your helmet.
我的…我的头盔?
My... my helmet?
欧丁神需要一个地方给你塞好吃的
Odin needs a place to put your goodies.
对 我会…找找看的
Yeah, right, I'll... get on that.
真是棒极了
Great.
等等
Hold on.
等等 好了 拜托
Hold on. All right, come on.
你在想什么? 别想了
What's on your mind? Out with it.
已经三天了 爸爸
It's been three days, Dad.
我只是在想 无牙这时会回来的
I just thought Toothless would be back by now.
我可以肯定它正和其它龙在一起
I'm sure he's with the other dragons.
嗯 我希望我也可以这么肯定
Yeah? I wish I could be that sure.
听着 我知道这就像是每年的这个时候失去了你所爱的人
Listen, I know what it's like to miss someone you love this time of year.
但我们能为他们不能留在这过节做些什么呢
But what do we do when they can't be here for the holiday?
我们应该为它们而庆贺
We celebrate them.
我敢说这正是无牙希望你所做的
And I imagine that's exactly what Toothless would want you to do.
-对吗 -你说得对
- Right? - You're right.
那就好 现在去找你的头盔吧
Good. Now go get that helmet.
我们已经够诅丧的了
We've had enough disappointment around here.
哦 Fishlegs 你很饿吗 这些鱼足够喂一条龙了
Oh, Fishlegs, you hungry? There's enough fish there to feed a dragon.
一条龙 那…
A dragon! That's...
Meatlug
Meatlug!
哇
Whoa!
Hiccup 你要去哪?
Hiccup? Where are you going?
我不知道
I have no idea!
Meatlug 礼物怎么办
Meatlug! What about presents?
嘿
Hey!
-我不能相信他 -你不能相信他?
- I can't believe him. - You can't believe him?!
-你绑了你的龙 -听起来我很卑鄙
- You kidnapped your dragon! - That makes it sound so mean.
-嘿 大家… -当它一被释放
- Hey, guys... - He flew away the second
-它就立马飞走了 -我72%确信
- he was unleashed! - I'm 72 percent sure
它想留在这
he wanted to stay.
-伙计们 -哇
- Guys! - Whoa!
Meatlug吐了一堆石头在这
Meatlug barfed up a pile of rocks.
你个白痴 这不是石头 你的龙生蛋了
You're such an idiot. Those aren't rocks. Your dragon laid eggs!
嘿 等等 我知道龙为什么要离开了
Hey, wait. I bet that's why the dragons left.
-去生蛋繁衍 -但公龙又不会生蛋
- To lay their eggs. - But boy dragons don't lay eggs.
你的公龙其实是条母龙
Yeah, your boy dragon is a girl dragon.
好吧 这正好解释了一些事情
OK! That actually explains a few things.
嘿 每个人都失去了他们的龙 对吧
Hey! Everyone's missing their dragons, right?
-又来了 -我想到了一个主意
- Here it comes. - I've got an idea.
这将会成为另一种新的Snoggletog节传统
It'll be another new Snoggletog tradition.
这主意实在太赞了
This is gonna be so good!
Meatlug 你要带我去哪?
Meatlug, where are you taking me?
你们来这里是为了繁衍后代
You guys come here to have babies.
哇
Whoa.
嗯
Hmm.
噢
Aww.
哇
Wow!
嘿 看这里 你落了一个
Hey, look over here. You missed one.
哇
Whoa!
天啊 它们不在博克岛孵化真是一件好事
Man, it's a good thing those don't hatch on Berk.
-这难道不是一个很棒的主意吗? -嗯哼
- Wasn't this a great idea? - Uh-huh!
每个人都会感到非常惊喜
Everyone is gonna be so surprised!
嗷
Ow!
真是惊喜啊
Surprise!
嗷
Aww!
龙蛋爆炸了?
The eggs explode?
龙蛋爆炸了
The eggs explode!
对不起
Sorry!
救救我们
Save us!
-赞 -哇
- Awesome! - Wow!
这仍然是你最棒的主意
This is your best idea yet.
雷神又搞什么鬼
What in Thor's name is going on?!
龙蛋爆炸了
The eggs explode.
无牙
Toothless!
Toothless?
来吧 无牙 你在哪里
Come on, Toothless, where are you?
Hookfang
Hookfang!
Stormfly
Stormfly.
哦 你们都不知道我看到你们有多开心
Oh! You have no idea how happy I am to see you guys.
你有孩子了?
And you have... babies?
看看你们大伙 多开心啊
Look at you guys, all happy together.
谁知道你们离开是为了庆祝你们自己的节日呢
Who knew you were leaving to celebrate your own sort of... holiday?
我也应该回去过我的节日了
I should get back to my holiday.
你有什么要说的吗 Hookfang
So, what do you say there, Hookfang?
你可以送我回家吗?
Think you can give me a ride back home?
当你们准备好回博克岛时我们再见面 好吗
I'll see you all back on Berk when you're good and ready. OK, gang?
不 不 不 不 不 我想我刚发起了一场还乡移民大行动
No, no! No, no, no! I... think I just started the return migration.
好吧 如果你们坚持的话
Well, if you insist.
来吧
Come on!
老兄 这行不通啊
Boy, this is never gonna work.
等等 我有办法了
Hold on. I've got just the thing.
老天 这真是一场灾难
Gobber, this is a disaster.
-没那么糟 -没那么糟?
- It's not so bad. - Not that bad?
村子被毁了 龙又离我们而去
The village is destroyed, the dragons have gone and left us...
让我们勇敢面对 这个节日是一个彻底的…
Let's face it. This holiday is a complete...
这些人在看啥呢?
What are these people looking at?
那是什么
What is that?
是Hiccup
It's Hiccup!
和我们的龙
And our dragons!
-欢迎回来 小伙子 -干得好
- Welcome back, laddie! - Good job!
耶 哇哇
Yeah! Whoo-hoo!
Meatlug
Meatlug!
Stormfly 你回来了 哦
Stormfly! You're back! Oh!
还有这些龙宝宝
And there are babies!
-做得好 儿子 -谢谢 爸爸
- Well done, son. - Thanks, Dad.
大伙 带上你们的龙 去大厅
Everyone, grab your dragons! To the Great Hall!
我们终于有事可以庆祝了
We finally have something to celebrate.
这是史上最棒的节日
This is the best holiday ever!
谁是宝宝? 谁是可爱的宝宝?
Who's a baby? Who's a cutie baby?
Hiccup 我知道你一定很难过
Hiccup, I know this must be really hard for you,
只能眼巴巴地看着每个人和他们的龙玩
seeing everyone with their dragons.
但你真的做了一件了不起的事情
But you really did a wonderful thing!
谢谢你
Thank you.
Astrid 无牙会去哪了呢
Astrid, where did Toothless go?
我不知道
I don't know.
哇 老兄
Wow. Man!
你现在后悔了?
Wouldn't wanna be you right now.
我是说 你带回了每个人的龙 除了你自己的
I mean, you brought back everyone's dragon except yours.
对 你知道吗 这一点帮助都没有
Yeah, you know, this is not helping at all.
无牙 嘿 伙计
Toothless! Hey, bud!
Stoick
Stoick.
坏龙 超级大坏龙
Bad dragon! Very bad dragon!
你要把我吓死了 再也不许在外面呆那么久了
You scared me to death! Don't ever stay away that long again!
你嘴里塞了什么
And what is in your mouth?
好恶心
Eww! Eww!
嗯 你找到了我的头盔
Yeah, you found my helmet.
嘿 你找到了我的头盔
Hey! You found my helmet!
你是去找我的头盔的?
That's where you've been?
伙计 谢谢你
Buddy, thank you.
你真棒
You are amazing.
Snoggletog节快乐
Happy Snoggletog!
我来了 无牙
I'm coming, Toothless!
好了 伙计 下来 我只是…
All right, bud, come on down. I was just...
无牙 你把这玩意拿出来干嘛 你再也不需要它了
Toothless, what'd you pull this out for? You don't need this any more.
来吧 我们走
Come on, let's get going.
你能不能别四处晃荡了? 你现在有新尾巴啦
Would you quit fooling around? You have your new tail now.
无牙
Toothless!
无牙 停下 你在干什么
Toothless! Stop! What are you doing?!
冬天在博克岛持续了很长一段时间
Winter in Berk lasts most of the year.
大发寒威 久久不愿离去
It hangs on with both hands and won't let go.
唯一让人真正感到暖和的对抗严寒的办法
And the only real comforts against the cold
是与心紧紧相依
are those you keep close to your heart.
好了 伙计 准备好了吗
OK, bud, you ready?
咦嗬
Yee-haw!
那是最棒的一个Snoggletog节
Turns out that was the best Snoggletog ever.
那年 我送了一件很棒的礼物给我最好的朋友
That year, I gave my best friend a pretty great gift.
哇呼
Whoo-hoo!
它给了我一件更好的
He gave me a better one.
翻译: 榕树下的守望者
yipeng.lofter.com